<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Culture | Bill Green]]></title>
  <link href="http://prgreen.github.io/blog/categories/culture/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://prgreen.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-30T03:05:04-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://prgreen.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Green]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vine is the new haiku]]></title>
    <link href="http://prgreen.github.io/blog/2013/09/13/vine-is-the-new-haiku/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-13T01:15:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://prgreen.github.io/blog/2013/09/13/vine-is-the-new-haiku</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What is the consequence of forcing users to an incredibly constrained six seconds video format?</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>The meaning is condensed. No more 5 minute video with only a few seconds of interesting action you could have skipped to directly. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Consistency is enforced. There is just no time to tackle multiple subjects or be distracted from your original point.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Ease of use. Anyone can make a 6 second video. Following the rules is not the hard part. </p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="its-twitter-all-over-again">It’s Twitter all over again</h2>

<p>The major trap with Vine or Twitter, or any fixed form of communication (haiku, sonnet, etc.), is that most people are tempted to use them for spontaneous (and usually meaningless) outbursts, when they should be carefully crafted and thought out for maximum impact.</p>

<h2 id="can-vine-really-be-advertised-as-a-new-art-form">Can Vine really be advertised as a new art form?</h2>

<p>In itself, Vine is only a vector for communication. It’s up to the people to use them as they want, the same way Twitter is used differently by brands, celebrities, ‘gurus’, teenagers, etc.</p>

<p>Conciseness has never been an obstacle to depth, and Vine is certainly capable of harboring art.</p>

<p>Sure, a lot of Vine videos are ADHD kids doing pointless crap, the same way most tweets are random angsty comments you could live without, and most haikus are mediocre attempts.</p>

<p>It doesn’t mean the form is flawed, but that it is used in frivolous ways.</p>

<p>Vine is currently experimental and teeming with general bizarrerie. But we can expect that it will stabilize, and that the same thing will happen to Vine that happened to Twitter:</p>

<p>People will learn to use it effectively.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speech is slowly becoming an obsolete emergency-only communication protocol]]></title>
    <link href="http://prgreen.github.io/blog/2013/09/12/speech-is-slowly-becoming-an-obsolete-emergency-only-communication-protocol/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-12T13:55:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://prgreen.github.io/blog/2013/09/12/speech-is-slowly-becoming-an-obsolete-emergency-only-communication-protocol</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Observing the real world you can notice this trend:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>People in social situations (parties, conferences, dates…) texting on their smartphone instead of speaking to other people.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>People in companies preferring to communicate via a collaborative textual chat, rather than speaking, sometimes with people a few feet away.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Young people who have no idea how to express themselves with words, people interviewed by television stumbling constantly for words, etc. ; when in the good old times, it seems people were generaly more articulate and confident speakers. </p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>People don’t like to speak anymore? We can try to understand the reasons why.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Speaking is not as necessary as it used to be. Alternative ways are simpler, usually require no formal greetings or keeping your attention focused, and are asynchronous (fire a text and forget about it until your friend reads it), while speaking requires synchronization of participants. Asynchronous is the future, the programmers say!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Speaking is vulnerable to ambient sounds. Our bustling modern world has constant background noise. Talking in public transportation can become tiring or tedious, while texting is still fine. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The information in everything you say is immediately lost if it’s not recorded or remembered. This is incredibly wasteful compared to text protocols.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>People spend more time communicating on social media, because it catches their interest by design, and they feel that maintaining a relationship with friends is more important than striking up random conversations with strangers, which are always hit-or-miss.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Speech is always unfiltered. And you don’t decide who gets to talk to you or not. For example panhandlers can choose to harass you with their voice, but they can’t reach you on your smartphone. Arguably, writing notes or texts to you would be somewhat less impactful anyway.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You need to start the speaking procedure by something like “Hey” and close it by something like “OK, see ya”. If your start directly talking about what you want to say, or just walk away when you’re finished talking, you’re a psycho.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Speech is not as easily processed by computers in meaningful ways. Speech recognition is still awkward to use.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You might have to repeat yourself a lot to make sure all people hear/understand you well, especially on the phone.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Feeling ignored while talking is the worst feeling. Feeling ignored while texting is a more subdued form of reject.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>In conclusion, it’s possible to argue that trying not to speak too much is an optimization, a way towards a better attention/information ratio.</p>

<h2 id="why-do-we-even-speak">Why do we even speak?</h2>

<p>OK, let’s not kid ourselves, the power of speech is important. Historically it was our best communication protocol for millions of years, a major turning point that confirmed the slow separation from our monkey cousins.</p>

<p>But really look at it from an exterior perspective: it’s a flawed and archaic protocol in the modern world.</p>

<p>The only advantages of speech compared to other communication protocols are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>The ability to broadcast a message to multiple geographically close persons easily.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Sensing involuntary body language and how feelings influence voices. This use of speech is especially irreplaceable in situations where you want to evaluate whether a person is trying to oversell him/herself, during dates, job interviews, business meetings, etc. You would never consider doing any of these activities through just a mail exchange.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Making sure you have the complete attention of someone. A good “Hey!” will always have priority over whatever the person is involved in.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Shouting to warn someone of an impending danger.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Objectively in an “augmented human” society where everyone has access to a communicating device, you could replace every use case of speech by text protocols, except maybe in case of emergency.</p>

<p>Well even then, I suppose you could implement differentiated ringtones or sound alerts depending on the content or special hashtags of the texts you receive on your smartphone.</p>

<p>But sound is not the most urgent or highest priority protocol available to mankind. When someone punches you in the face or kisses you on the mouth, their intent is obvious and immediately brought to your attention.</p>

<p>Smartphones being capable only of text and sound (as of today), it’s fun to imagine how the world would be changed if they could act physically on you, via a bluetooth extension in your brain to control you, for example.</p>

<p>Why be content with your smartphone triggering a sound alarm as it detects a bus with broken brakes coming right at you, when your smartphone could trigger your body to get out of the way, without wasting time to think, and with an unbeatable reaction time?</p>

<p>Shy in public? Not confident with your body language in the presence of women? Preload your smartphone with a selection of prerecorded body language from the most confident public speakers in the world, specifically tuned to the tastes of your target audience, and let your bluetooth brain extension direct your every move!</p>

<p>So yeah, the world is changing.</p>

<p>If the current evolution of technology is prolonged to its logical conclusion, it’s safe to assume everything you know about humanity might be unrecognizable in a hundred years.</p>

<p>I suspect speaking might become truly unnecessary once humans are all equipped with wireless binary data transceivers wired to a hybrid processor/brain.</p>

<h2 id="what-about-speech-commands-xbox-one-ps4-kinect-ps-eye">What about speech commands, Xbox One, PS4, Kinect, PS Eye?</h2>

<p>Don’t they prove that speech, and body language, and all archaic forms of communication, are the future?</p>

<p>A <em>modern</em> trend to focus on speech and body language, the two most primitive communication protocols available to mankind? How could that be?</p>

<p>And what about virtual reality and the buzz around Oculus Rift? It seems using the “natural” protocols of humanity and have the computer adapt to you, instead of asking unnatural things like pressing buttons, or entering text commands, is the future of gaming, or what?</p>

<p>I’m not the only one to think it’s not progress, although most people would have a difficult time articulating why.</p>

<p>Simply these technologies cater to people’s monkey brains, trying to increase sales by having the simplest requirements possible, the lowest common denominator, using communication protocols that everyone, even your mother, even your grandmother, use everyday.</p>

<p>And guess what, it works. People who would never play video games can understand that making the gesture of punching someone will hurt enemies, running will make you run, etc.</p>

<p>No need to press buttons anymore (a physical way of sending binary data!) to make the console do things, you talk and order it, like you would in a normal social situation.</p>

<p>Is it the future of gaming? At least it’s a way to attract more people to video games, younger kids, seniors, families, etc.</p>

<p>But the “energy spent”/”fun” ratio is really bad, and the more obsessive “optimizing” gamers will obviously find no interest in that, and are not the target audience anyway.</p>

<h2 id="ok-so-no-speech-then-whats-in-the-future">OK, so, no speech… then what’s in the future?</h2>

<p>The most refined way you can interact with a gaming console is not speech or moving your arms around: it’s basically a computer, so the best way for it to understand what you want is… just programming it.</p>

<p>Pressing buttons means forcing the game program to follow different parts in the code based on your stream of binary input. What if you had more freedom than that, and could actually script your interactions with the games, essentially having your own code as a part of the game?</p>

<p>I would not be surprised if the future of gaming was just that: games where you interact with a world by programming parts of it.</p>

<p>Of course programming is hard for our monkey brains, we’re slow at it and make a lot of mistakes, it’s not always fun, which seems to defeat the purpose of a game. But we might evolve to a point where computers are so ubiquitous that programming skills are a required part of being a normal human being, just like basic math or speaking a natural language is required for every normal human being now.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Evolution towards a unique language for all humans is inevitable]]></title>
    <link href="http://prgreen.github.io/blog/2013/09/12/evolution-towards-a-unique-language-for-all-humans-is-inevitable/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-12T11:09:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://prgreen.github.io/blog/2013/09/12/evolution-towards-a-unique-language-for-all-humans-is-inevitable</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is obviously a sensitive subject, especially when so many countries make deliberate efforts to preserve their own language.</p>

<p>Objections to a unique language make sense:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>A language perpetuates the culture of a people or nation (litterature, laws, concepts, are shaped by language).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>People will never give up their mother tongue willingly, so a unique language would have to be enforced globally with totalitarian techniques, and you don’t want that.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>No one language is capable of expressing everything perfectly.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You’d need a consensus on which language humanity would adopt.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>People will prefer learning multiple languages rather than fully adopting a common one.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>People will break any attempt of a unique language by inventing their own words, simplifying, creating new ones, modifying the pronunciation, language is an ever evolving process and nothing can be set in stone once and for all.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>All these objections are valid. In reality, evolving towards a unique language is already taking place, English being obviously the favored global language for business, trade, etc.</p>

<p>The need for a common ground with people you interact with is made more pressing by the Internet. The days are past, when most people would spend all their life speaking only to their geographical neighbors.</p>

<p>By personal experience I can say that the “invasion” of English into the French language, for example, is felt strongly as a threat by the older French generations, and not so much by the young, who are now taught English from age 7, even before they know how to use their mother tongue properly.</p>

<p>No one will be able to stop the process. After all, in year 3000 French is already a dead language.</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://prgreen.github.io//www.youtube.com/embed/7osGfFTQVtU?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Regional languages of French (they are plentiful… France is a gathering of multiple old “tribes”, not just Paris) are even more doomed, they are in fact already dying and a historical curiosity rather than functional languages, despite ongoing revival attempts in French schools. Strong regional accents that can be found easily among seniors are softened by the influence of the uniform accent of television and other mass media.</p>

<p>I even read about English middle-aged persons appalled by some young people sounding more and more American. </p>

<p>Of course everywhere where people are isolated, or in ghettos, or when specific efforts are made to preserve a language (French in Quebec for example is unlikely to just die out), the uniformity can never fully reach them.</p>

<p>Now imagine this “connected” future, maybe dozens or hundreds of years from now, everyone using exclusively social media and talking through cybernetic implants, not only with people closer to them geographically, but with people from all over the world with the same interests.</p>

<p>If this is indeed the evolution of the world, all languages will eventually die out except one.</p>

<p>Just by interacting, you lose your specificity, your idiosyncrasies must be abandoned. I can’t speak regional <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Picard_language">Picard</a> anymore (yes, just like the Star Trek captain, this is not a mere coincidence) when I’m in California, and it’s unlikely my future children will ever hear a word of it, while my grandparents used to speak it almost exclusively.</p>

<p>A world where everybody interacts constantly with everyone, like in social media, tends to be more uniform. The French youth watch Breaking Bad. Because it’s discussed everywhere on Twitter. The French youth use the invented frenchized verb “liker” instead of “aimer”, for Facebook likes.</p>

<p>Emotionally rejected by many, fearful of a George Orwell’s dystopian <em>Newspeak</em>, a unique language would make (and already makes, since you’re reading this blog and you’re not necessarily a native English speaker) pragmatic sense.</p>

<h2 id="is-english-the-answer">Is English the answer?</h2>

<p>You could argue that English is already the common language of the world, and in many ways it obviously is. Sadly, English is broken, and it shows. </p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>It’s a bastard language, so there are <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_English_words_with_dual_French_and_Anglo-Saxon_variations">multiple words</a> for many things when one could theoretically be enough and greatly simplify the learning process for people all over the world.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can’t know the correct pronunciation of a word by just reading it, if you never heard it pronounced before.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Vowels in general are shifted in various crazy ways. You can never be sure (shoor? shir? shor?) which one is preferred in this or that part of the world.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A rather simple and elegant grammar crippled with unfortunate bizarre exceptions (not as bad as French, though).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The pronunciation of English, “accents”, stressing words and sentences properly, is very hard for a lot of nations in the world. It’s all musical and slippery, when strong syllabic pronunciations (in French, German, Japanese) feel more consistent in this area. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Even when you’re comfortable with, say, a generic American accent, you can have all sorts of trouble understanding the crazy British local accents.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Can there be, conceptually, a language “good enough” that it could boast the necessary paradigm shift required for immediate and durable global adoption?</p>

<p>Of course many tries have been made historically, to form a language that everyone in the world could speak easily, some with reasonable success (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esperanto">Esperanto</a>).</p>

<h2 id="what-would-be-the-desirable-properties-a-common-language">What would be the desirable properties a common language?</h2>

<p>It would be nice if it were strongly logical, consistent, and with no ability to diverge from the original idea.</p>

<p>In our current world, with our current monkey brains, it’s close to impossible. We have poetry, ambiguity, play on words, litterature, portmanteaux, our languages are wild and free, which is arguably a good thing.</p>

<p>But imagine a future, thousands of years from now, where human beings are half-robots with incredible computing power wired to their brains, capable of enforcing rules strongly, and they spend all their time discussing with every other person on a hive-like Earth.</p>

<p>It’s possible humans will not even speak or write anymore, just exchange data instantly in binary form, wirelessly.</p>

<p>The following properties can be achieved, making natural languages an inferior alternative:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>our unique language has no ambiguity. Everything is expressed clearly. No intent is ever misunderstood.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>our unique language can easily be processed by computer programs. Sentences in natural languages can be formally verified and then used as integral parts of mathematical proofs. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>our unique language punishes any divergence from the accepted norms by being rendered automatically incomprehensible when even one bit of it is invalid.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>While it sounds like a 70s novel futuristic dystopia, it would at least make the programmer’s task considerably easier.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
